<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://www.sibawayhi.org/schema/2010/07/monograph"
	 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	 xmlns:sib="http://www.sibawayhi.org/schema/2009/07/sibawayhi"
	 xmlns:typog="http://www.sibawayhi.org/schema/2010/08/typog"
	 xmlns:xlit="http://www.sibawayhi.org/schema/2010/08/xlit"
	 xml:id="background">

  <label>ref:genre</label>
  <title>Genre</title>

  <p>
    Use of a variety of distinct genres rooted in Mamluk literary
    practice is one of the major hallmarks of Zayni Barakat.  We have,
    in addition to "ordinary" narrative: the traveler's journal;
    reports of intelligence agents; proclamations and announcements
    from the Sultan or other authority figures; letters; etc.
  </p>

  <p>
    Question: what genres would the author single out as distinctive,
    or having distinct identity?  What does the author take to be the
    distinctive rules associated with each genre?
  </p>

  <section>
    <title>Herder on Genre</title>

    <p>Quotes from Forster, "Herder on Genre", in "After Herder"</p>

    <bq>Virtually all forms of linguistic communication, and many non-linguistic ones as well, essentially belong to one genre or another - the scientific article is as much a genre as the novel, the stump speech as much as either, the portrait sculpture as much as any of the preceeding. (p. 163)
    </bq>

    <bq>"... the central role that the identification of genre plays in interpretation..." (p. 163)
    </bq>

    <bq>
      "Herder does ... imply ... a sort of informal definition: a
      genre is constituted by an overall purpose aimed at some class
      of works, together with certain rules of composition which serve
      that purpose." (p. 165)
    </bq>

    <bq>
      "Correct identification of a work's genre is vitally important
      for two main reasons... First, it is essential for properly
      understanding the work, for interpreting it correctly.  Why is
      this so?... (i) identifying a work's genre is in itself an
      essential aspect of fully understanding the work... (ii) There
      will normally be aspects of a work's meaning which are
      expressed, not so much by any of its particular parts, but
      rather through its exempification, as a whole, of a certain
      genre... (iii) Correct identification of a work's genre is also
      necessary in order properly to understand meanings that are
      expressed by the work's parts....  Second, in Herder's view,
      correctly identifying a work's genre is also essential for
      evaluating the work properly." (p. 167-8)
    </bq>

    <bq>
      "It is part of Herder's position here that a genre is always
      rooted in a specific cultural context from a specific time and
      place, and that in order to identify it correctly ... one needs
      to see it in relation to its cultural context." (p. 174)
    </bq>

    <bq>
      "... continuity in the words used and/or other superficial
      similarities in fact mask myriad different concepts.  ... therer
      is a major task of investigating unfamiliar concepts in order to
      identify them correctly, and thereby make proper interpretation
      (and evaluation) possible; a constant threat to acheiving this
      deriving from a temptation falsely to assimilate alien concepts
      to ones with which the interpreter is already familiar and which
      superficially resemble them; and also a potential for an
      indefinite amount of conceptual innovation in the future, in
      continuation of that which has taken place in the past."
      (p. 176)
    </bq>

  </section>

</chapter>

